The Egyptians Invent
Writing.
The valley of the Nile had developed a high stage of civilization while people in Europe were still living in caves.
The Egyptians have taught the Western world many things.
They were excellent farmers.
They knew all about irrigation.
They built temples which were afterwards copied by the Greeks and which served as the earliest models for churches.
They had invented a calendar which proved such a useful instrument for the purpose of measuring time that it has survived with a few changes until today.
Most important of all,
the Egyptians had learnt how to preserve speech for the benefit of future generations.
They had invented the art of writing.
We are so accustomed to newspapers and books and magazines that we take it for granted that the world has always been able to read and write.
As a matter of fact,
writing, the most important of all inventions,
is quite new.
In the first century BC,
the Romans came to Egypt and found the valley full of strange little pictures.
These queer figures covered the walls of the temples and of the palaces and endless reams of flat sheets made out of the papyrus reed.
It seemed to have something to do with the history of the country,
but the Romans were not interested in the foreign culture and did not inquire into the origin of these pictures.
The last of the Egyptian priests,
who had understood the holy art of making such pictures,
had died several years before.
Deprived of its independence,
Egypt had become a storehouse,
filled with important historical documents which no one could decipher.
Seventeen centuries went by and Egypt remained a land of mystery.
Then,
in the year 1798,
the French general Napoleon Bonaparte marched his army into eastern Africa to prepare for an attack upon the British colonies.
He did not get beyond the Nile,
and his campaign was a failure.
But,
quite accidentally,
the famous French expedition helped solve the mystery of the ancient Egyptian picture language.
One day a young French officer,
bored by the dreary life of his little fortress on the Rosetta River,
one of the rivers at the mouth of the Nile,
decided to spend a few hours exploring the ruins of the Nile Delta.
There he found a stone which greatly puzzled him.
Like everything else in Egypt,
it was covered with little figures.
But this particular slab of black basalt was different from anything that had been discovered before.
It carried the same text written in three languages.
One of them was Ancient Greek,
which was still known to many educated Europeans.
The French officer was greatly excited by his find,
as he believed it would finally solve the riddle of the Egyptian script.
He reasoned that all that was necessary was to compare the Greek text with the Egyptian figures and they would reveal their secret.
Though the plan sounded simple enough,
it took more than twenty years to solve the riddle.
In 1702, a French professor named Champollion began to compare the Greek and the Egyptian texts of the now famous Rosetta Stone.
In the year 1823,
he announced that he had discovered the meaning of fourteen little figures.
He died a short time later,
but not before deciphering the main principles of Egyptian writing.
Today,
the story of the Valley of the Nile is well known throughout the world.
We possess a written record which covers 4,000 years of chronicled history.
The ancient Egyptian hieroglyphics,
the word means "sacred writing",
is one of the earliest known systems of writing to be used by humans,
the other being the ancient Chinese script.
It is not surprising then that some of the Egyptian symbols,
in modified form, have found their way into the modern European alphabet.
It is important to understand that ancient Egyptian writing did not consist of drawings of objects,
such as the ones drawn by early humans on the walls of caves.
It was not a sign language.
It was an ingenious system of writing consisting of symbols to represent sounds and words,
invented close to 10,000 years ago,
to preserve the spoken word.
Each symbol used in Egyptian hieroglyphics meant a great deal more than the object which they represented.
Let us try to understand how it works.
Suppose that you were Champollion and that you were examining a stack of papyrus sheets,
all covered with hieroglyphics.
Suddenly you came across a picture of a man with a saw.
Very well, you would say.
That means,
of course, that a man went out to cut down a tree.
Then you take another papyrus.
It tells the story of a queen who had died at the age of 82.
In the midst of a sentence appears the picture of the man with the saw.
Queens of 82 do not use saws.
The picture, therefore, must mean something else.
But what?
That is the riddle which the Frenchman finally solved.
He discovered that the Egyptians were the first to use what we now call phonetic writing,
a system of characters which reproduce the sound,
or phone, of the spoken word and which make it possible for us to translate all our spoken words into a written form with the help of only a few dots and dashes and pot hooks.
Let us return for a moment to the little fellow with the saw.
The word 'saw' either means a certain tool which you will find in a carpenter's shop,
or it means the past tense of the verb "to see".
This is what had happened to the word during the course of centuries.
First of all, it had meant only the particular tool which it represented.
Then that meaning had been lost and it had become the past participle of a verb.
After several hundred years,
the Egyptians lost sight of both these meanings and the picture came to stand for a single letter,
the letter S.
A short sentence will show you what I mean.
Here is a modern English sentence as it would have been written in hieroglyphics.
The first symbol either means one of the two eyes in your head,
which allow you to see,
or it means I,
the person who is talking.
The second symbol is either an insect which gathers honey,
or it represents the verb 'to be' which means 'to exist'.
Again, it may be the first part of a verb like 'be come' or 'be have'.
In this particular instance,
it is followed by a symbol which means 'a leaf' or,
or leave.
The sound of all three words is the same.
The 'I' and the 'saw' you know about.
Finally, you get the picture of a giraffe.
It is part of the old sign language out of which the hieroglyphics developed.
You can now read that sentence without much difficulty.
"I believe I saw a giraffe."
Having invented this system,
the Egyptians developed it during thousands of years until they could write anything they wanted,
and they used it to send messages to friends,
to keep business accounts,
and to keep a record of the history of their country that future generations might benefit by knowing about the past.